Guide to the Robert A. Hill Collection, 1890-2014 RL.10993
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Primary Sources (PS), 1859-1991 and undated; 8
  - Black Nationalism Churches and Organizations, 4
    - The Athlian Heart - The Constitution of the Afro Athlican Constructive Gaathly, Inc., 1928 Sep 30 (Box PS13)
    - The Athlian Green Pasture Company deed, shares, payment book, 1929, 1930, 1937 (Box PS13)
    - The Athlian New Light of the World, 1927; 3 copies, fragment (Box PS13)
    - Correspondence - Henry Yubudela to Shepard Robert Athlyi Rogers, 1932 Feb 25 (Box PS13)
    - The Gaathyl's Gate - Afro-Athlican Constructive Gaathly, leaflets, 1925 (Box PS13)
    - Hamatic Church hymn book, 1926 (Box PS13)
    - Join the Gaathly, leaflet, undated (Box PS13)
    - The Living and Trading Scheme, undated (Box PS13)
      "The Living and Trading Scheme was first made known to the Afro, Athlycan constructive Gaathly."
    - Report of marriage - James Green and Georgia Barber Nash, 1929 Jul 27 (Box PS13)
      Shepherd Athyli Rogers officiated the marriage.
    - Maragh, G.G. - The Promise Key, undated (Box PS13)
      G.G. Maragh is a pseudonym for Leonard Percival Howell
    - Blyden, Edward W. - Christianity, Islam and the Negro Race, Samuel Benjamin papers, 1888 (Box PS13)
    - Biographies - Andrew, Muriel Rogers, 1978 (Box PS13)
      Includes a biography of Robert Athly Rogers.
    - Ethiopia Calls/We Will Rally/Universal Tribulation - Rastafari chants, undated (Box PS13)
    - The African Orthodox Church Its Declaration of Faith, Constitution, and Canons and Episcopate, (Hill 8), 1921 (Box PS14)
      Includes the history of A.C.E. League, and a list of death benefits paid.
    - Alexander, Rev. Daniel William, African Orthodox Church, undated (Box PS14)
    - Services of Synod of African Orthodox Church, 1927 Sep 7-12 (Box PS14)
    - The Trumpet, The Official Organ of the African Orthodox Church, Volume I, Number 4, 1964 Feb-Mar (Box PS14)
    - Big Bethel AME Church correspondence, 1915, 1922, 1933 (Box PS14)
    - Our Book - - Good Will Magazine, Vol. 2, No. 3, 1942 Sep-Oct (Box PS14)
      Published in Cleveland, Ohio
    - Our Book - - Good Will Magazine, Vol. 3, No. 2, 1943 Feb (Box PS14)
    - Adorkaville, A Church Community, Laura Adorka Kofey, Professor Leonard Barrett papers, undated (Box PS14)
    - The African Messenger, Laura Adorka Kofey, Professor Leonard Barrett papers, undated (Box PS14)
    - African Universal Hymnal, Laura Adorka Kofey, Professor Leonard Barrett papers, undated (Box PS14)
    - Bantu Primer Book, Laura Adorka Kofey, Professor Leonard Barrett papers, 1968 Jul 16 (Box PS14)
    - The Church - Why Mother Established the Church and What It Stands For, Laura Adorka Kofey, Professor Leonard Barrett papers, undated (Box PS14)
    - Mother's Sacred Teachings, Laura Adorka Kofey, Professor Leonard Barrett papers, undated (Box PS14)
    - Mother's Sayings, Laura Adorka Kofey, Professor Leonard Barrett papers, undated (Box PS14)
    - Moody, Harold A. - The Colour Bar, 1945 (Box PS14)
    - Moody, Harold, M.D., B.S. - Freedom for All Men, 1945-1946 (Box PS14)
    - Father Divine - The New Day, Vol. III, No. 4, 1939 Jan 26 (Box PS14)
    - Oyekan, Owomoyela - African Literatures: An Introduction, 1979 (Box PS18)
    - Alexander, Rev. Daniel William - African Orthodox Church, undated (Box PS18)
    - The Negro Worker letterhead, undated (Box PS18)
    - Back to Africa group photograph, undated (Box PS18)
    - Biographical Sketch of Booker T. Washington, Tuskegee Institute Press, undated (Box PS18)
    - Walter Rodney Poster, Center for Afro-American Studies, UCLA, 1981 Jan 30 (Box PS21)
    - Rogers, Robert Athalyi - Negro Map of Life: The Way From Earth to Heaven, annotated, 1917 Apr 15 (Box PS21)
      Map and drawing of The United Home and Bank of the Negroes.
    - Mission Crusader, Out of Africa The Public Ministry and Assassination of Mother Kofi, March 8, 1928 circular (Box PS21)
    - Prophet Athlyi, Holy Piby, Garvey as apostle - newsclippings, 1927-1928 (Box PS22)
    - The Pacific, 1934 Feb (Box PS22)
    - Constitution and By-Laws of the Pacific Movement of the Eastern World, 1933 (Box PS22)
    - USA vs. Pacific Movement of the Eastern World - legal record, 1943 Aug 11 (Box PS22)
    - Takada, Lima - photography / Pacific Movement of the Eastern World - ID card, undated (Box PS22)
    - The Afro Athlican Constructive Gaathly banners, undated; 26.5x80" and 27.5x51" (Box PS26)
  - Rastafarianism, 1941-1992, undated
    This subseries includes origianal materials related to Rastafarianism Robert Hill used as research sources for projects including The Rastafari Bible and are arranged chronologically.
    - Great Ancient Brotherhood of Silence (GABOS), Ethiopian Mystic Masons letter, 1941 Jun 29 (Box PS27)
    - Ethiopian National United Defence Association No. 1, Flier, 1951 (Box PS27)
    - Standing the Gap by the Seventh Emmanuel's Bretheren, Flier, 1960 Jan 15 (Box PS27)
    - A Look at the Black Struggle in Jamaica, African Youth Movement, 1969 (Box PS27)
    - It's the People Who Must Govern, Youth For Social Change, Pamphlet, 1972 (Box PS27)
    - A Memory on Count Ossie - Ras Dizzy, 1976 Oct 20 (Box PS27)
    - Pan-Africanism, Rational and Irrational - Ian Duffield, 1977 (Box PS27)
    - Howell, Leonard Percival - Last Will and Testament, 1980 Apr 12 (Box PS27)
    - Song of Our Redemption, Printed by Black International Iyahbinghi Press, 1986 Jun (Box PS27)
    - Blackhearts, Essay - Dawta Kate, 1989 (Box PS27)
    - Ethiopia Africa Black International Congress Church of Salvation, Flier, 1992 (Box PS27)
    - Ethiopian Guild and Brotherhood Nation, undated (Box PS27)
    - Joshua, Aaron, Moses, Eli. - Two Months of Selling Out Jamaica, Abeng Group, Pamphlet, undated (Box PS27)
    - Pacific Movement of the Eastern World, Certificate of Membership, undated (Box PS27)
- Jamaica Materials (J), 1940s-2013
  This series contains original materials, secondary research, and facsimiles and transcriptions of primary sources that chronicle the International Peacemakers Association and Rastafari Movement in Jamaica from the 1950s to 2013. Hill collected these materials, in part, for his Dread History: Leonard P. Howell and Millenarian Visions in the Early Rastafarian Religion (2001), in which he explores Rastafarianism. While Hill gathered his research from the 1980s to 2013, some materials have been given their original date.
  - International Peacemakers Association, 1941-1978
    The International Peacemakers Association contains original materials relating to the Jamaican commune founded by Rev. Claudius Henry in Green Bottom, Clarendon in 1966. The photographs, correspondence, financials, and other items found in this subseries focus on the activites of Rev. Henry, his wife Edna, and their followers. Robert Hill visited the commune in 2010 during a research trip for his response to M.G. Smith, Roy Augier, and Rex Nettleford's report, "The Ras Tafari Movement in Kingston, Jamaica." Materials are described at item and folder level.
    - Mounted color photographs, undated; 10 items (Box J1)
      Photographs relate to the International Peacemakers Association. Some photographs are duplicates from the Rev. Henry Picture Album.
      - Photo 1, undated; 1 item (Box J1, Print RL.10993-P-001)
        A tent-like structure surrounded by large palm leaves.
      - Photo 2, undated; 1 item (Box J1, Print RL.10993-P-002)
        A group of people standing in front of a worship facility with a sign that reads "Israel's New Creations Healing Balm House to Let the Oppressed Go Free and that Ye Break Every Yoke."
      - Photo 3, undated; 1 item (Box J1, Print RL.10993-P-003)
      - Photo 4, undated; 1 item (Box J1, Print RL.10993-P-004)
        Three men standing in front of a worship facility with a sign that reads "Israel's New Creations Healing Balm House to Let the Oppressed Go Free and that Ye Break Every Yoke."
      - Photo 5, undated; 1 item (Box J1, Print RL.10993-P-005)
        A worship facility with a sign that reads "Israel's New Creations Healing Balm House to Let the Oppressed Go Free and that Ye Break Every Yoke."
      - Photo 6, undated; 1 item (Box J1, Print RL.10993-P-006)
        A fenced worship facility with a sign that reads "Israel's New Creations Healing Balm House to Let the Oppressed Go Free and that Ye Break Every Yoke."
      - Photo 7, undated; 1 item (Box J1, Print RL.10993-P-007)
        A choir singing.
      - Photo 8, undated; 1 item (Box J1, Print RL.10993-P-008)
        A choir and others gathered around a pulpit.
      - Photo 9, undated; 1 item (Box J1, Print RL.10993-P-009)
        A man being baptized in the baptismal house.
      - Photo 10, undated; 1 item (Box J1, Print RL.10993-P-010)
        A woman being baptized in the baptismal house.
    - Framed print, "Black Picture of Christ", undated; 1 item. (Formerly boxed as J2.) (Print 1)
      "Black Picture of Christ" by Sherman Schofield Furr.
    - Rev. Henry picture album, 1960s-1970s; 1 item (Box J3)
      The album contains photographs and descriptions relating to the International Peacemakers Association, a compound founded in Green Bottom Clarendon, Jamaica in 1966. It focuses on the activities of Reverend Claudius Henry, his wife Edna Henry, and their followers. It includes photographs of the Ethiopian Peacemakers School of Ancient Traditional Bible History, the International Peacemakers Musician Group, the Peacemakers' Tabernacle, the Baptismal House, the Ark, the Peacemakers' Bakery, the Peacemakers' bread vans and brick oven, the Royal House of David, and Edna's Memorial Park. Most of the individuals appearing in the photographs are identified by group. Individuals identified by name include Claudius and Edna Henry, Ronald Trevor Henry, Michael Joshua Manley, Roy McKay, and Rudolph Gordon.
    - Rev. Henry correspondence and financials, 1941, 1969-1978, undated; 10 folders (Box J4)
      Contents Include: loose photographs; Barclays bank statements and deposit book; receipts; correspondence related to the International Peacemakers Association; International Peacemakers Association event programs; and Jamaica Agricultural Society Incorporation Act/Amendment.
    - International Peacemakers Association posters, undated; 1 folder (Oversize-folder 1)
      Posters display photographs of key leaders, such as Claudius Henry and Roy McKay, as well as Haile Selassie. The posters outline the central tenets of the International Peacemakers Association and the Ten Commandments.
  - Research, 1959-2013; 1,580 folders
    The subseries contains notes, annotated readings, newspapers, correspondence, and facsimiles of primarary sources that cover the Rastafari Movenent and International Peacemakers Association. Content may overlap with Research (RE).
    Research is described at box level and arranged alphabetically. Materials are in original order. Multiple runs of alphabetical files were generated at different times and not interfiled.
    - African Religions through Richard Burton, 97 folders (Box J5)
      Contents Include: African religions, Apocalypticism, anti-white propaganda, aculturation, Abrahamic religions, Joseph Solomon Ashby, African Revolutionary Movement, Moses Baker, Book of Mormon, Boboshanti Camp, Bobo Dreads, and Richard Burton.
    - Black Supremacy through Edith Clarke Papers, 106 folders (Box J6)
      Contents Include: Black Supremacy, Barnes Foundation, Back-to-Africa Movement, Martha Beckwith, Jeanne Christensen, coronation of Ras Tafari, chronology, Rabbi Bishop Cook, Cuba, CIA, Cult of Rastafari, creole religions, Cargo Cult, and Edith Clarke Papers.
    - William Crowdy through Dreadlocks, 95 folders (Box J7)
      Contents Include: William Crowdy, Circuit Court of Kingston, H. Dunkley interview, Dead Sea Scrolls, Vivian Durham, King David, Dominica, Dread Library, and dreadlocks.
    - Ras Dizzy through Gleaner Headlines, 95 folders (Box J8)
      Contents Include: Ras Dizzy, divine kinship, Prince Emmanuel Edwards, Ethiopia, Evangelicalism, Ehtiopian Zion Coptic Church, Father Divine, French Guiana, Gramsci, and Gleaner headlines.
    - Robin Horton through Holy Piby, 93 folders (Box J9)
      Contents Include: Robin Horton, Richard Hart, heresy, holiness, hierocracy, Holy Piby, and hair.
    - Issemble of Elders through Kongo Prophetism, 105 folders (Box J10)
      Contents Include: Issemble of Elders, Isaiah, Rev. Samuel Johnson, Jerusalem, Jamaica Archives Depot, Jamaica Journal, Jamaica Times, Kumina, Kingston, and Kongo Prophetism.
    - W.A. Lewis through Douglas Mack, 108 folders (Box J11)
      Contents Include: W.A. Lewis, Gordon Lewis, Melchizedek, Malachi, mysticism, Moorish Science Temple, and Douglas Mack.
    - Bob Marley through Planno, 94 folders (Box J12)
      Contents Include: Bob Marley, Maccabees Bible, Nyabingi, newspapers, New Religions Movement, Jalani Niaah, Otto, Old Testament, and Planno.
    - Pariah Intellectuals through Rastafarite Cult, 67 folders (Box J13)
      Contents Include: Pariah Intellectuals, Charles Price, Pocomaniacs, Pentecostalism, Planno, Ken Post, Pinnacle Papers, police report, Queen of Sheeba, and Rastafarite Cult.
    - Rastafari Bible through Rastafarianism, 81 folders (Box J14)
      Contents Include: Rastafari Bible, Revivalism, Rastafari organizations, Ratafarian women, religious movements in Central Africa, Rastafarian art, and Rastafarianism.
    - Rastafarianism through Salvation Army, 94 folders (Box J15)
      Contents Include: Rastafarianism, Rasta Bible, Rastafari bibliography, Rasta documentary films, M.G. Smith, spiritualism, street preaching, and Salvation Army.
    - Haile Selassie through Vodou, 98 folders (Box J16)
      Contents Include: Haile Selassie, South African Rastas, Swaby, Syncretism, M.G. Smith, treason, topical index of scripture, UNIA, and Vodou.
    - Vow of the Nazarite through Zionism, 70 folders (Box J17)
      Contents Include: Vow of the Nazarite, witchcraft, Welsh Revival, Watchtower, Carol Yawney, and Zionism.
    - Research notecards, undated; 4 folders (Box J18)
    - Newspaper research, 1960-2013; 2 folders (Box J18)
    - National Archives research, 1959; 5 folders (Box J18)
    - Research, unsorted, 1980-2013; 13 folders (Box J18)
    - Research correspondence, 2005-2010; 1 folder (Box J18)
    - African Salvation Society through Coptics, 44 folders (Box J19)
      Contents Include: African Salvation Society, AmConGen, Bishop Brown, black Pentecostal churches, Biblical references, cults, and Coptics.
    - Bishop William Saunders Crowdy through Septimus Higgins, 52 folders (Box J20)
      Contents Include: Bishop William Saunders Crowdy, Church of the Living God of the Twelve Apostles System, dreadlocks, Ras Daniel, Ethiopia Progressive Association, Ethiopian World Federation, Marcus Garvey, Garveyism, and Septimus Higgins.
    - J.N. Hibbert through Kapo, 71 folders (Box J21)
      Contents Include: J.N. Hibbert, Claudius Henry, Italo-Ethiopian War, Imperial Ethiopian World Federation, Jamaica religious cults, Julius Jerome, Kumina, and Kapo.
    - Kumina through Obeah, 43 folders (Box J22)
      Contents Include: Kumina, locks, Elliot Leib, Myalism, Millenarianism, McGregor, Nabingi, Nyabinghi, and Obeah.
    - Father Joseph Owens through Rastafari Bible, 70 folders (Box J23)
      Contents Include: Father Joseph Owens, Pentacostal Holiness Church, Polomanism, Revivalism, Rastafari Movement, Rastafari Manifesto, Rasta Voice Magazine, and Rastafari Bible.
    - Rasta Letters through Zionists, 65 folders (Box J24)
      Contents Include: Rasta letters, Rastafari Bible, Rastafari cults, Rastafari International Theocracy Assembly, Salvation Army, Haile Selassie, Shashemane, M.G. Smith, George Simpson, Carole Yawney, Zion in Jamaica, and Zionists.
    - Halo-Ethiopian War Petition signatures, undated; 1 folder (Box J25)
    - First International Rastafari Conference, undated; 1 folder (Box J25)
    - Ethiopianism Jamaica, Q. Zullenzar, 1933-1939; 1 folder (Box J25)
    - Coptic Time, 1978-1979; 1 folder (Box J25)
    - Coptic Times, 1978-1979; 2 folders (Box J25)
    - Map of Jamaica, 1984; 1 folder (Box J25)
  - FBI, 1959-1964, 2011-2013; 24 folders
    FBI is described at folder level and arranged by date and topic. It includes research requests from Robert A. Hill to the FBI in his efforts to gather documentation on Claudius and Ronald Henry, the Rastafari Cult, and Rastafari Movement. Other materials, such as counterintelligence briefs, foreign service dispatches, and Canadian military service records, can be found here. This subseries may overlap with Hill's FBI research in Microfilm (MF) and Other Works (OW).
    - FBI research and related documents, 1959-2013; 14 folders (Box J26)
    - New York City Police Department Bureau of Criminal Identification, 1960; 2 folders (Box J26)
    - FBI records, Claudius Henry and Ronald Henry, 1960; 5 folders (Box J26)
    - FBI records, Rastafari Cult, 1959-1964; 2 folders (Box J26)
    - FBI records, Rastafari Movement, 1961; 1 folder (Box J26)
  - Transcriptions and Keyword Searches, 1923-1962, undated; 293 folders
    Transcriptions and Keyword Searches is described at folder and box level and arranged both chronologically and alphabetically. It includes transcriptions of newspaper articles, correspondence, and other materials, all of which are related to the Rastafari Movement and the International Peacemakers Association. As a general rule, the annotation is attached to a copy of the original document. Content may overlap with transcriptions and keyword searches in other series.
    - Transcriptions, National Archives, 1923-1962, undated; 134 folders (Box J27)
      Transcriptions cover topics such as communism, Ras Tafari, Rastafarians, Ethiopian World Federation, Emperor of Ethiopia, Haile Selassie, the People's Freedom Movement, the People's Political Party, Rev. Claudius Henry, and Ronald Henry.
    - Transcriptions, newspapers and correspondence (letter), 1959-1961, 1981-2010; 95 folders (Box J28)
      Transcriptions cover newspaper articles, such as the Daily Gleaner and Jamaica Times, periodicals, and correspondence. Topics include the Back to Africa Movement, Rastafarians, Rev. Claudius Henry and his trial, Ras Dizzy, and Rastafarian Cult.
    - Transcriptions, unsorted (letter), 1959-1961, undated; 9 folders (Box J28)
    - Keyword searches, 2004, undated; 16 folders (Box J28)
      Keyword searches mostly pertain to Biblical figures and scriptural references.
    - Appendices, undated; 1 folder (Box J28)
    - Research correspondence, 1990-2013; 1 folder (Box J28)
    - Transcriptions, newspapers and correspondence (legal), 1960-1962, undated; 37 folders (Box J29)